A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Cabell-Carrington Papers 1776-1852, ca. 1000 items.
  Papers of the Cabell and Carrington families of Albemarle and Buckingham counties and Richmond. The letters of Agnes Gamble Cabell to her stepdaughter Louisa Cabell (later Carrington) are a rich source of ante- bellum family life. They provide insight into the life of a well-to-do young woman's life in early 19th century Virginia. Correspondence spans 1817-1862 and touches upon education, health and medicine, slave life, politics, gossip, mother and daughter relations, child-rearing and romance. One letter dated February 28, 1819, warns Louisa that one of her beaux is part Indian (Not Native-American) and she will have to pass him by as well as his cousin. However, Agnes also warns her daughter not to be too picky because "not, I would have you all to understand, that I am in a hurry to have you married, but, married you must be some time or other, as the world goes." Also a comment on Thomas Jefferson's grandson, Thomas Randolph, being stabbed severely by his brother-in-law, Bankhead," a worthless profligate fellow." Letters from 1819-1822 concentrate on Louisa's marriage and her child and also a mysterious illnesses that she succumbs to, which was called melancholia, but more likely post-partum depression. Her mother Agnes also gives birth during this time. Letter dated March 2, 1822 Agnes to Louisa contains much advice concerning Louisa's baby and she is sending baby caps, "for myself, I trust I shall have no further use for them." A letter dated May 25, 1824, Agnes admonished Louisa for trying to nurse her own child as it will cause her injury. Agnes would have sent Easter (presumably a slave) to nurse the child if she had known, "but we permitted her to dry up her milk." In November of 1825, Louisa gave birth to a girl after two sons, Agnes writes: "Will Paul and William be cast off for this little Miss?-not entirely-but I think you will perceive a difference in the kind of affection you will feel for your little girl-though not in the degree, you will love them all equally, but she will have more of your tenderness. (November 2, 1825)." A very strong collection. Related materials, the letters of Laura Wirt to Louisa Carrington, are in 2546. #2447
- Joseph Carrington Cabell Papers 1759-1882, 2270 items.
  Papers of various members of the Cabell family, chiefly the papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell (1778-1856), a member of the Virginia legislature for thirty years, one of the founders of the University of Virginia and a member of its first Board of Visitors. Includes much correspondence of women touching on such subjects as daily life, religion, education and medicine. Highlights are the letters Joseph Carrington Cabell wrote to St. George Tucker requesting the hand of his step-daughter, Mary (Polly) Walker Carter in marriage. These letters provide a valuable insight into Virginia eighteenth century courtship among the plantation class. Also of interest are several letters from both Mrs. Ann Cowper and her husband, William Cowper to Joseph C. Cabell about the disintegration of their marriage, and Mrs. Cowper's request for divorce in 1812. There is also information on the detaining of a Parsons Taylor, a fencing instructor at the Richmond Academy, for seducing six female students. #38-111.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Additional Papers 1857-1860, 1 volume.
  Fourteen-page volume (many pages missing) containing recipes and formulae for dyeing, recorded by Sallie Syme (Cabell) Laidley, Inglewood, Nelson County, Virginia, later of Richmond. #38-111-a
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Additional Papers 1860-1959, 120 items.
  Papers and photographs of the Cabell family, especially of Captain John Cabell (1775-1815), Eva Cabell, and members of the Borgardus, Simpson, and Perkins families, and including an album of carte-de-viste of Cabell family members. Of notes are the letters to Eva Cabell, wife of William Russell Robinson, which coincide with the Civil War period. Letters from Peachy G. Harrison to Eva Cabell describe his general experiences during the war. #38-111-b
- William Daniel Cabell and Mary V. Ellet Cabell Papers 1830-1890, 3600 items.
  Correspondence, diaries, and other papers of Mary Virginia Ellet Cabell, her father, Charles Ellet, Jr., civil engineer, of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and her husband William D. Cabell of Norwood, Nelson County, Virginia, relating primarily to Mrs. Cabell's career as author and civic leader. Collection includes a thousand letters from Mrs. Cabell to her children, material on Norwood school, data on the Daughters of the American Revolution. Mary Ellet was William Daniel Cabell's second wife, and the letters he wrote to her during their courtship are very passionate in nature. Mary, however, is practical in her responses, perhaps because she had responsibility for her younger siblings, Willie and Nina, and marriage was not on her mind. The letters between husband and wife reflect the structure of a 19th century marriage, however, Mary Cabell comes across strongly as an independent thinker and her husband very reliant on her. Correspondence touches on almost every issue from literature to politics. #276-a
- Virginia Moffett Fletcher Caldwell Letter 1984 and 1985, 2 items.
  Caldwell sends greetings to Cornelia and Waller Barrett, describes Erskine's and her month of travel, asks about the Barrett's new home, and encloses a photograph of a painting recently delivered to the Jamison Gallery in Santa Fe, Mexico. With these is a postcard, 1985, from "Kate" to the Barretts describing a trip to Poe's house in Philadelphia and Whitman's in Camden. #7971-n
- Bessie Callender Letter 1898, 1 item.
  Letter (carbon typescript), September 13, 1898, from Bessie Callender to Emily Eppes of Appomattox Manor, Hopewell, Virginia, describing "Cawsons," the birthplace of John Randolph of Roanoke, and mentioning news of her family. #3545.
- Carr Family Papers ca. 1745-1880, ca. 1500 items.
  Personal and business papers of the Carr family and George Carr of Albemarle County, Virginia. Also included are a photograph of a black woman (Poore family) and a May 6, 1868 letter about the death of a black woman. #4869, etc.
- Elizabeth (Ambler) Carrington Papers 1796-1825, 25 items.
  Included are typescript copies of correspondence between Elizabeth Carrington, nee Betsy Ambler, and Mildred Smith, 1780-1782, discussing her experiences during the Revolutionary War, the flight to Charlottesville, Virginia to escape the British and the destruction of Yorktown, Virginia. #6723
- Mrs. Tazewell Carrington-World War II Collection 1937-1946, ca. 1000 items.
  The collection primarily consists of letters from servicemen to Mrs. Carrington, as well as newspaper clippings, photographs and other miscellaneous items. The collection is restricted; no publication until 2026. #2585
- Henry Rose Carter Letters 1902, 1904, 1934, n.d., 9 items.
  Letters of Carter, George E. Booker, James C. Reed, and Anna Barringer. Miss Barringer's letter concerns the placement of this collection of letters relating to Walter Reed. #3568
- Sally Champe Carter 1813-1827, 12 items.
  Gossipy letter, December 21, 1827, from Sally to her mother, Mrs. Mary Carter concerning her stay in Richmond. #38-582-a
- Carter Family Papers 1800-1885, ca. 70 items.
  Letters, diplomas, valentines and other papers of the Carter family of "Redlands", Albemarle County, Virginia, including the correspondence of Sally Champe Carter Randolph, Mary Eliza Coles Carter, Isaetta Carter and others. #2704
- Carter-Smith Papers 1726-1870, ca. 2700 items.
  Materials on the Carter, Coles, Smith and Nicholas families. Primary interest centers around General Samuel Smith and his son, John Spear Smith of Baltimore, Maryland, and his daughter Margaret who married Robert Hill Carter of "Redlands," Albemarle County, Virginia. Sizeable amount of correspondence generated by women. #1729
- Wilson Miles Cary Papers 1820-1914, ca. 2000 items.
  Papers of the Cary family, especially that of Wilson Miles Cary (1806-1877) of Charlottesville, Virginia, and later of Maryland, and that of Archibald Cary (1815-1854), of Cumberland County, Maryland. Highlights include letters between Jane Margaret Carr Cary (Mrs. Wilson Miles Cary) and her mother, Hetty Carr (1829-1832), and between Jane Margaret and her cousin Dabney Carr Terrell, who traveled extensively in Kentucky and who describes a reception for Lafayette. Also of interest are the Civil War letters. Jennie and Hetty, daughters of W.M.C. and Constance, daughter of Archibald Cary, frequently crossed into Confederate territory, and detailed these crossings in letters. Some of the correspondence relates to the house searches to which the Carys were subject as Southern sympathizers. #1415
- Carysbrook Memoir 1860-1865, 2 items.
  Written by Mrs. Jane Blair Cary Smith (1808-1888), a granddaughter of Col. Thomas Mann Randolph, who penned these memoirs of Carysbrook in Fluvanna County, Virginia while living in New York. The original memoir does not exist, however, it was copied by the author's nephew. #1398
- Elizabeth Branch Cave 1831-1834, 1 item.
  Friendship book of autographs kept by Miss Cave while a guest at Rockbridge Alum Springs. Microfilm 548; (#3527).
- Neilia Cave Letter 1864, 14 items.
  Letters, January-September 1864, from Cave to Major John P. Thompson, a prisoner of war of Johnson's Island near Sandusky, Ohio. #3527-c
- Percy W. Charrington Papers ca. 1870-1939, ca. 20 items.
  Diaries, notebooks, and photograph albums of Charrington, diary, 1939, of T. H. Ashley-Cooper; diary, 1872-1873, of Jane Randolph; letter, March 1, 1934, "Your loving sister E" from Monte Carlo, to Mamie and Ernest Ashley-Cooper, concerning her activities there. Randolph's diary contains personal entries about herself, moving from their old home, her father looking at land in Fauquier County, Virginia (September 1872), the Radford family, staying in Lynchburg, Virginia, and other miscellaneous personal entries. #3603
- Chicago Women's Club 1896(1929), ca. 25 items.
  Pamphlets, brochures, newspaper clippings and correspondence relating to the Chicago Women's Club. #72
- Civil War Letter 1862-1864, n.d., 6 items.
  Letter from William H. Girrell (Ginell?) to his sister Becca during the Civil War. Letters are full of confidences, obviously Becca and her brother were very close. #1618
- Civil War Letter 1861, 1 item.
  Letter, September 3, 1861, Aunt Charlotte to her nephew Clarence, congratulating him on his marriage. She touches upon the Civil War and trusts Clarence will remain a strong Union Man. She says she is absorbed by the war and hopes it will speedily end. #38-382
- Civil War Letter March, 1865, 1 item.
  Letter from Laura to Edith describing Sheridan's raid on Charlottesville, Virginia. #2929
- Cleaveland Family Papers 1858-1901, ca. 100 items.
  Papers of A. H. Cleaveland and Eva Cleaveland including one scrapbook of clippings, recipes, and personal accounts of Eva Cleaveland (1879-1901), music teacher and choir director in Charlottesville, Virginia. #1999
- Clements-Dinwiddie Papers 1831-1907, 28 items.
  Miscellaneous in regards to the Clement and Dinwiddie families of Franklin County, Virginia. Most papers refer to land and business, but there are two items of note: a playbill 1952 for the opera singer Adelina Patti and a cover from a bankbook of the Bank of the United States. The inside has a clever "love-letter." #2819
- Harry and Jeannie Clemons Papers March 1927, 5 items.
  Notes on Nanking, typescript copies of Harry and Jeannie Clemons' narrative of the Nanking incident, China of 1927, with letters explaining them from Mr. Clemons to Mr. Berkeley. There is mention of the evacuation of women and children, with specific references to female friends and acquaintances. #3550
- The Clocks Social Club Papers 1839-1935, 7 items.
  Relates chiefly to Richmond, Virginia blacks and includes a minute book for The Clocks Social Club detailing the regular and business meetings of the club, and recording dues and attendance. Also included are a list of sewing instructions: a letter, February 1935, to the Clocks urging them to buy tickets to hear the Eva Jessye Choir at the Ebenezer Baptist Church: a copy of the Rev. John Jasper's sermon "De sun do move" and a photograph of Jasper. Of interest is a letter, February 11, 1839, from Sarah McPhail, Franklin, Tennessee, to her brother, Thomas Glass, Winchester, Virginia, giving family and farm news and mentioning the loss of a Negro woman. #8979-u
- Mary Taylor Clough Poetry 1826, 194 boxes
  Bound volume of handwritten poetry of Clough. #3522
- John Hartwell Cocke Papers 1725-1939, 194 boxes
  The remarkable set of complete plantation records of John Hartwell Cocke of Bremo, Fluvanna County, Virginia. John Hartwell Cocke is less known than many of his contemporaries, but remains one of the most extraordinary men of his time. He co-founded the University of Virginia with Thomas Jefferson, waged war against the evils of alcohol, strongly supported education, and was an outspoken opponent to slavery, so much so that he educated his slaves and then set them free. Many returned to Africa and the ensuing correspondence between the former master and the free man makes for fascinating reading. There is also a rich amount of material regarding women's history, in particular 19th century plantation life. Of special interest are the diaries of Louisa Maxwell Homles Cocke, the second wife of General Cocke. #640.
- Lucy C. Cocke Diaries 1850-1853, 3 items.
  Diaries of Lucy C. Cocke. With accession 640. #1335-a
- Lucy Williamson Cocke Diary 1864-1868, 1 item
  Lucy kept her diary from 1864 to 1868. It contains recipes, poetry, religious passages and news of the war. An excellent source for the war and women. #6846-i
- Philip St. George Cocke Papers 1848-1860, 4 items.
  Personal correspondence of the family of Philip St. George Cocke. In her letter of February 9, 1846, Courtney Barraud of Norfolk, Virginia writes her cousin, John Bowdoin Cocke, that she has heard about "the big house" being begun and knows that "cousin Philip" will be very busy as "no one ever was more totally emersed in building." In an undated letter to her father, Philip St. George Cocke, Louisiana Barraud Cocke, is apparently defending Richard Byrd Kennon, whom she married on June 21, 1860; she relates that she "asserted my pride & dignity as a woman should" by speaking to Kennon about the conversation between him and her father, and that she is satisfied that he is sincere and that she has not been "the dupe of anybody."(2433-t)
  Also, letters to John Bowdoin Cocke (P. St. G. Cocke's son) from John H. Powell, principal of the Richmond Female Seminary concerning the progress and tuition fees of Cocke's three daughters (1886-1894), also correspondence of Sally Elizabeth Courtney Cocke to her husband P. St. G. Cocke.(2433-r).
  Of further interest are the letters of Courtney Bowdoin Cocke to various family members concerning family news, travels, activities and plantation matters (2433-q).
  Lastly, the letters dealing with the prolonged courtship, engagement, and eventual marriage of Bettie Burwell Page Cocke and John Bowdoin Cocke are of interest, as well as later letters which detail the effects the Civil War had on Southern land-owning families. (2433-l) #2433-t,-r,-q,-l.
- Coxe-Dinwiddie Family 1722-1919, 10 items.
  Miscellaneous items, of interest is a typescript of the household book, 1722-1729, of Anne Coxe Harris. #2820
- College Presbyterian Church, Hampden-Sydney n.d., 1 item.
  A history of the Church by Miss Sallie Dickinson. #38-497.
- Colonial Dames of America in the State of Virginia 1900, 1 item
  Bound clipping in regard to the Colonial Dames #2057
- Commencement Address 1859
  Commencement address by an unidentified president of an unidentified woman's college, probably delivered in 1859. The question of female education is discussed. #477
- Commonplace Books ca. 1860-1895, 3 items.
  Three illustrated albums or commonplace books, The Landscape Album, The Lady's Album, and Token of Love, with various manuscript insertions indicating their owners were Anna Johnston, Hannah Hayward, and Sara Pauline Fullings, Northern Presbyterian missionaries. The manuscript insertions reflect the broad travel experience of these ladies. #1689
- Elizabeth Edmonia (Churchill) Berkeley Cooke 1855-1858, 1 item.
  Diary kept by Mrs. Cooke at "Dewberry," Hanover County. #1197-a
- Coolidge-Jefferson Collection ca. 1790-1840, ca. 300 items.
  Mainly personal correspondence of Thomas Jefferson's descendants, especially Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge, his granddaughter. #9090
- Coolidge-Randolph Collection 1814-1836, 41 items.
  Group of letters from Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge and others to Martha Jefferson Randolph. #38-384
- Anna Cornell 1831-1834, 1 item.
  Commonplace book kept by Anna Cornell of Millstone, New Jersey includes poetry and essays by friends and family members and obituary of Anna's mother, Maria Cornell. Many of the pages contain small engravings or watercolors. #6526-j
- Maria Cosway Letters 1786-1789, 24 items.
  Maria Cosway, an English miniature portrait artist, met Thomas Jefferson in Paris and would become what some historians declare to be the love of his life. These collections represent some of their correspondence. #1683, 1804, 2043
- Cox-McPherson Family Papers 1758-1949, 209 items.
  Personal and business correspondence of the Cox and McPherson families including: Bible records for the children of John and Elizabeth Humber; the Cox and the Lacy families; and printed material concerning the Women's Christian Temperance Union. Other items in the papers include: a photograph of Miss Almera Josephine Cox and her four nieces, Amelia Foster Christian Cox, Annie Leroy Cox, Mary Elizabeth Cox and Almira Josephine Cox, who were all children of Leroy Wesley Cox and Ann Eliza Foster Cox. #38-11
- Almera Cox Papers 1859, 10 items.
  Report cards for Almera Cox at the Albemarle Female Institute. #2223
- Mary V. Crenshaw Papers 1913-1921, ca. 300 items.
  Correspondence and material relating to her life as a librarian. #3289
- Mary Lee Custis 1830, 1 item.
  Copy book of Mary Lee Custis, mother-in-law of Robert E. Lee. #2584
- Dabney Family Papers 1850, 1 volume.
  John Dabney's personal recollections of several family members, including many women. #3234
- Dabney and Davis Family Papers ca. 1800-1970, ca. 13,000 items.
  Personal correspondence of these central Virginia families, primarily of Richard Heath Dabney and his wife Lucy Heth (Davis) Dabney. Included is a February 10, 1867 letter, from Alice Dabney (a former slave) to "Old Master." #9852
- William Meade Dame Papers 1859-1931, ca. 100 items.
  Papers concerning William Meade Dame of Danville, Virginia. Letters concern his time spent as a Confederate soldier, a seminarian in the Episcopal Seminary in Alexandria, and as a Episcopalian minister. Very strong on religious issues, social life of Danville (and Virginia) after the War, and family activities. Correspondence of Susie Meade (William's wife), his mother, Mary Dame, and his sister Ellen. #2145.
- John Warwick Daniel Papers 1816-1936, 14,000 items.
  Papers of John Warwick Daniel (1842-1910), U. S. senator and Civil War Veteran, and his family. The earliest correspondence, 1816-1825, is between Judge William Daniel (1771-1839), his wife Margaret Baldwin) Daniel (d. 1824), and their children, of Lynchburg, Virginia. The letters contain news of family and friends, advice on manners and education to children, and mention of medical treatments. These papers are an excellent source for the study of family life and women's role in the early 19th century. Also of importance are the letters Sarah Warwick Daniel between William Daniel, Jr. #158
- Margaret Dashiell Letter May 24, 1944, 1 item.
  Margaret Dashiell to Samuel Love, writes about her health, reading material and World War II. #1976
- Alice Chancellor Davis Papers 1913, 1 scrapbook
  Scrapbook of Alice Chancellor Davis containing postcards and other memorabilia, and notes of a trip made to England, Scotland and Ireland in 1913. Also included is the correspondence of John White, later Alice Davis' husband. #58-a
- Eugene Davis Family Papers 1744-1925, 350 items.
  Papers of Eugene Davis of Charlottesville, Albemarle County, Virginia concerning the Civil War, temperance, slavery and hospital conditions in Charlottesville before and after the War. The collection includes a 19th century copy of a bond, July 19, 1791, between Thomas Meriwether and Ann Minor; a letter to Eugene Davis from the Ladies of the Albemarle Relief Association which provided assistance to the families of dead or disabled Confederate veterans; and scattered correspondence from women. #2483, -a
- John Staige Davis Letters 1862, 3 items.
  Letter, October 13, 1862, from Mary Quincy to Davis, thankful for news of her son and offering assistance in the future to soldiers who come through her area. #3638-a
- Day-Martin Family Papers 1885-1921, 1000 items.
  Correspondence and other papers of the Day family of Smithfield, Virginia, and of senator Thomas S. Martin, who married Lucy Day. Items of interest are the letters to both Lucy Day and Grace Day concerning their engagements, letters of condolences to Mrs. Charles Fenton Day on the death of her husband. Also included are Grace Day's journal of her trip to Europe, 1901, and her touching letter to her mother upon the death of Mr. Day. #38-159
- Daughters of the American Revolution Papers
  Virginia D.A.R. program of 43rd annual convention, Jack Jouett chapter, yearbook for 1935-36 and Member's List, 1938-1939. #412
- Daughters of the American Revolution Papers 1916-1984, 20 items.
  Scrapbooks, minutes and membership applications of the Shadwell chapter of the D.A.R. #10524, etc.
- Daughters of the American Revolution Papers 1968-1971, 3 items.
  Volumes contain newsclippings of state and divisional D.A.R. activities. #6884-h
- Daughters of the American Revolution, Blacks Fort Chapter n.d., 1 item.
  Minutes describe activities at several monthly meetings. #9073
- Daughters of the American Revolution Papers 1891-1974, 7 items.
  Material relating to the Albemarle Chapter of D.A.R. #3106, a-e
- Varina Jefferson Davis Letter April 13, 1895, 1 item.
  Varina Davis to Mrs. A. H. Thomas regretfully declining an offer to visit Alexandria, Virginia. #3152
- Deale Family Papers 1860-1865, 10 items.
  The letters of Theophilus Deale to his father, mother, and sister. #2664
- Aurelia deBoots Letter 188?, 1 item.
  Aurelia deBoots to Felix [?]. Mrs. deBoots, as she apparently was, wrote to Felix to inform him that his son (and most likely her son) had been accepted by "poor unsuspecting de Boots," evidently her husband. #38-647
- Sally Bruce Dickinson, Irish Creek School 1912-1922, 11 items
  Items include Schools taught by Miss Sally B. Dickinson; a biography Miss Sally Bruce Dickinson; My education had limitations and My first experience as a teacher by Miss S. B. Dickinson, and information on Irish Creek School in Rockbridge County, Virginia. #2699
- Dinwiddie Family Papers 1850-1940, ca. 2500 items.
  Manuscripts relating to the Reverend William A. Dinwiddie from 1857 and Elizabeth M. Dinwiddie, 1916-1940, of Albemarle County, Virginia. Other prominent people in the collection include Courtenay, Edgar, Emily, William, Jr., and Mrs. Mary Agnes Bruce. There are approximately 55 letters to Elizabeth M. Dinwiddie. Of special interest is Emily Dinwiddie's scrapbook concerning World War I and women's suffrage. Also included in the collection are papers relating to the Bryan family. #3194, -1
- Dixon Family Papers 1826-1836, 22 items.